We were the freak show
and we spent 20 years [music] for this
moment.
>> We're doing it. We're doing it. And I'm
sure you're enjoying this as much as I
am.
>> I just got three things to say. God
bless our troops. God bless America and
gentlemen
start your
>> We are the power that actually has the
decisive vote and that is with military
superiority. If Silicon Valley believes
we are going to take away everyone's
white collar job, you're the most
important [music] thing Palanteer is
doing is to make sure that American war
fighters are much more likely to come
home. If we are going to outperform the
rest of the world, our single advantage
is
Dr. Carp, it is a pleasure to finally
have the OG American Dynamism founder on
stage with us at the 4th annual summit.
Um I think gosh if we had
>> do this like [laughter] that.
>> Yes. Um I think if we had you guys don't
get that there's a gang signs.
[laughter]
>> No, I think we all got the the
reference. Um
>> Maddiey's in the audience. [laughter] He
doesn't get out much. He's like, "Huh?
What is that? This is going to be a
great conversation. So, I think uh if we
had this conversation 72 hours ago, it
would have been very different. Um but
of course there's been a lot of news and
so I want to get straight to to the news
and what's [snorts] happening in the
world. Um because Palanteer is certainly
um part of that story. So over the
weekend uh the US and Israel bombed Iran
and Operation Epic Fury. Ayatollah how
many is dead. The Middle East is now at
war. What do you think the situation
means for the future of the West?
Something you talk a lot about and the
future of America. Well, first of all,
I'm delighted to be on stage with you
and um you know, for many of you in this
audience, by the way, I'm I've been
talking so much I'm kind of losing my
voice, but I didn't I I would have
probably canceled on anyone but you. But
>> Oh, that that means a lot. We're glad
you're here. [laughter]
>> I love to cancel, by the way, for those
of you cuz like it's my favorite thing
cuz I I actually am an introvert. Any
excuse to cancel as as Palunteerians
know. It's uh Yeah. Um but yeah, you've
been such a force um in public and
behind the scenes for you know I think
helping people in the broadly speaking
defense tech or let America wins or
things that are good uh broadly defined.
Um, and then we also align on something
we could talk about later on, like the
importance of not putting our youth in
straight jackets because they're
divergent neurologically, which is a
passion of of mine and should be a
passion of everyone's since
>> you could define our wonderful and great
country as a country where everyone who
was divergent in ideology, thought,
religion or quite frankly like uh uh
neurologically came to this country to
have a better place where they could
express their freedom and had the right
to a express what they thought which and
there's a deep link between expressing
what you think publicly and privately
first and fourth amendment and being
able to think it and if that doesn't
work being able to defend it with the
second amendment uh and uh the and last
not least our our founders founders uh
uh did not structure these rights the
way they are in say where I lived for a
lot of my life in Germany as rights
granted to us by other bureaucrats. We
they're given to us. They're inaliable
from a higher being.
>> Uh and uh I would just say before I get
into uh how the world's changed, we have
American uh war fighters on the
battlefield. Uh s willing to sacrifice
their lives. Uh some of whom have
sacrificed their lives. They have
families and kids. Kids and families
don't know if their loved ones are
coming home. And uh you know we uh I
know in this room but we should publicly
privately support them and people who
are not aware or somehow so effing
spoiled that they don't realize what
these people do for us we should
publicly humiliate them. Uh and everyone
has a role in that. uh um and especially
those of us who are riding a crest of of
of
intergenerational cultural intellectual
courage advantage which it which it is
to be an American nowadays should not
obviously should not forget uh the war
fighter who are disproportionately
uh from uh the middle of our our country
and disproportionately have gotten
screwed
Uh and uh you know I'm proud uh very
proud that at Palunteer
uh you know we we get arrows and people
I mean half the people attacking us it'd
be good if they spent two minutes on
Wikipedia at least learning the talking
points they're regurgitating but uh but
um you know there's some legitimate
criticisms uh of any company but
at the end of the day the fact is the
most important thing Palanteer is doing
than I other people in this room are
doing and people like you and other
people adjacent or ancillary to building
uh uh more lethal and deadly weapons is
to make sure that American war fighters
uh are much more likely to come home and
quite frankly the people who are trying
to harm them uh know that they won't be
coming home and that's the way you stop
people from attacking us in my opinion
and then on the [clears throat] the kind
of um the leading up to what's going on.
But I think the there are probably
people in this room who are wildly
supportive uh and there are people who
aren't. It is hard to deny that America
is exerting a deterrent capability that
was eviscerated.
you you can like or not like that's
different than ignoring we now have a
deterrent capability that no other
country appears to have and that is for
for lots of reasons and obviously
uh the war fighter people organized the
war fighter the generals the leadership
the president
but one advantage that often gets
overlooked in it for reasons that make
no sense is war fighting is technology
ology, you know, I I spent half my life
in in in Germany for familiar reasons
and then I wrote my PhD there. It it the
and then the rise of America after World
War II, the reason America was able to
win World War II were technological
advantages. And if you look what
happened in, you know, Operation
Midnight Hammer, what happened in
Venezuela, what's so far happening uh uh
in in in Iran, you see one society just
totally dominating. That's our society.
Now, you could get into I I would I I'm
always in fights with my intellectual
friends about they're they're like, "But
wouldn't it be better to have a rule a a
law-based system where everyone is
equal?" Yeah, sure. in theory, but in
this world, it's us or China or Russia.
>> Yeah.
>> And I don't know how you guys feel about
those decisions, but I think we're doing
I literally believe we're doing the work
of higher a higher purpose by making
sure and not just for America, but for
the whole world that we are the power
that actually has the decisive vote. And
there is only one way to do that and
that is with military superiority. And
when I say military superiority, I don't
mean that we're arguing on a PowerPoint.
It means but America. So now you get to
what is technology done? Now again, I
think whenever people like me are
talking about this, it you can't say
enough that it's the war fighter and
their courage and I'm not doing that.
I'm sitting here um and you know and I'm
not and we have Palunteerians all over
on like I'm talking to them constantly.
So they're doing they're putting
themselves in harm's way and you know um
uh I'm I am kind of but not directly.
It's mostly all the people who yell at
me and I guess maybe there are some
people want to shoot at me but um it the
the the if you look at the rise of like
in the in the lifetime of Palunteer
there's been the rise of software which
essentially me meant your you know
software company that is supplying a
steak dinner that's obviously parasitic
is not cutting it that kind of those
those companies are being eviscerated
you the rise of defense tech and now you
have a hybrid software, hardware, AI
where you really need all three. Um,
interestingly from an investment
perspective, um, you know, I would say
the last company standing before we all
have to salute the overlord of the LLM
will be Palanteer. But it's mainly
[laughter]
>> we're going to get into that, I promise.
mainly because um you there it's it's
the specificity of and the security and
the orchestration
but none of that has to make any sense
to anyone in this room. I'll tell you
what it makes a lot of sense to our
adversaries right now. How is America
doing this? Now again it's specialized
ways. It's 25 30 years of experience in
fighting its meritocracy. The department
of war is the most meritocratic
environment. It integrated in Korea
before our society did. Uh it's it it is
the most popular institution
and most revered institution and
probably the only institution in America
that is actually revered by the American
people across every demographic. And
it's revered by the American people
across every demographic precisely
because it's been meritocratic. If if
you were a black American, uh you got
your break in America by going to the
military. if you wanted to be treated
fairly uh and you were from a group that
you felt that every demographic has
somebody who is in the military whose
life was changed and it did something
noble and wonderful for America. They
also have the experience of coming home
in America not sticking up for them. We
should change that. Now you get to
Silicon Valley. Uh my one message for
and again I I don't I'm without getting
in specific people or cuz I'm like
if Silicon Valley believes we are going
to take away everyone's white collar job
meaning primarily democratic shaped uh
people whom I grew up with highly
educated people who went to elite
schools or went to schools that are
almost elite who vote for one party and
you're going screwed the military. If
you don't think that's going to lead to
nationalization of our technology,
you're [ __ ] And you might be
particularly [ __ ] because you have a
160 IQ, but it you this is where that
path is going.
>> Like you cannot have technologies that
simultaneously take away everyone's job
and then be perceived. Again, there's a
lot of subtlety here behind behind the
curtain. I've been heavily involved in
that subtlety. what can be where it can
be deployed what can be deployed there's
a difference between US military and
surveillance and despite what everyone
thinks Palanteer is the
anti-surveillance company I know your
person online thinks that's not true but
every technical expert does so I end up
in every conversation that I don't want
to be in but the the danger for our
industry is that America you get a you
get a famous horseshoe effect where
there's only one thing people agree on
and that's that this is not paying the
bills and people and our industry should
be nationalized and and so the the the
societal benefit that is going on in
Iran besides the fact that I think I
suspect the Iranian people feel like
finally someone's on my side and it
wasn't the Berkeley faculty that was
supposed to like me. Uh [laughter] it
it's uh um a big lesson for you. Yeah.
So um and but then as America we and a
people who are prominent in the tech
industry, you know, we have to find a
way to make sure that we're not just
popular in PaloAlto.
>> Yeah. I I want to get back to something
you just said, which is that, you know,
that it's it's either us winning or
China winning or Russia winning or
another country that it's a zero- sum
game. And it feels like the people in
this room in Washington really
understand that AI is zero sum, but that
Silicon Valley doesn't. Silicon Valley
doesn't like to think in terms of zero
sum. They like to think that everything
is a positive sum game. So, how would
you explain to the people in Silicon
Valley who are again building the LLMs,
you know, building um what what they
would say is a brand new net new
technology that hasn't existed before
and therefore it needs to be treated
differently. What would you say to them
about this?
>> Well, I mean, there's so first of all,
it's it's um by the way, I just want to
push back slightly. They do think it's
zero sum. They think it's zero sum
versus each other.
>> So like they absolutely are fighting.
There will be like you know it's my own
rhetoric if I happen to think it's true.
It's going to be chips ontology and I
suspect in the end one one and a half
provider. So they pretend they don't
think it's zero sum but then ask them
how they feel about their competitor. So
it's very very I mean these people are
fighting very very hard for the dominant
position. So like what they don't
understand is in the world it's zero
sum. But I I actually think the primary
issue in the valley is it's going to be
zero sum visav
when America decides that look okay I
have I I interact with a lot of
political figures I have a lot of
respect I think in some are when
politicians figure out this is the one
winning issue it is going to be zero sum
it's going to be your money and your
company being zero sum nationalized so
that's the part they don't understand fe
helping people understand that, you
know, either we set the rules or deacto
like I'm I'm much more I'm much more on
America should be strong so that we
don't have to worry about the enemies
than our enemies are evil kind of thing.
So I'm not super neocon. It seems to be
very hard in this culture as someone
who's lived abroad a lot of my life.
It's very hard in this culture to
explain to people that we're in a
competitive environment because things
here are so good. They don't understand
how different it will be and how much we
will change and how much the pressure
will be on America, not just legally,
but militarily and culturally if we fall
behind. And I I I one of the things that
again it's so I I personally think the
better way to get people to change is to
>> okay it it Go bring people like that to
Iowa. Bring them to DC and explain to
our American political leadership why
you make hund00 million and why a
soldier from Iowa can't explain to his
wife he has the best technology and then
go across the hall. So let's classically
Republican shaped. Then go across the
hall and talk to progressive Democrats
about how everyone in their constituency
is not going to have a job. and then
leave and imagine what's going to happen
to you.
>> You know the funny thing about those of
us who've spent most of our life abroad
like in Germany which a phenomenal
culture we have a much better sense of
how fragile this exper experiment is
America it could go wrong
>> and it will go wrong if if all wealth is
going to a small number of people and
those people do not appear to be on side
now that perception might is obviously a
caricature. It is a caricature in the
sense this is new technology and you're
not going to be able to use the same
kind of framework and you're going to
need people who appreciate how it's
different and there are real questions
about fourth amendment protections like
our right to privacy. What is privacy in
a world where you could imputee what
someone's doing at home through
technology? H how do you protect our
right to have our own thoughts, our own
ideas, our own practices at home, our
own health records? that those are real
issues when the technology can also help
you to be healthier, live longer, uh
have a higher economic status
potentially, certainly if you're a
vocational worker. But so those issues
have to be unpacked. And where Silicon
Valley is right is you you're going to
need a forum to talk about that that
doesn't pretend, you know, large
language models is the same thing as
machine learning is the same thing as
software is the same thing as a bullet.
They're they're not. Yeah.
>> Um but um but but but but de facto I I
very much believe u as a critique of the
uh like economic elite especially in in
the technical area there's there's like
to use an econom a kind of overly
economic uh a philosophical term they
reify meaning they turn it into a thing
our rights but those rights you know
when I was in Germany I I was there and
there were I spent a lot of time I did a
PhD uh but I you know there were a lot
of older Germans and I I would spend
time with them in the countryside in the
city of course they they didn't know
anybody who was a Nazi in the
countryside they're like we were all
Nazis so I would ask them but one of the
more fascinating conversations is why
they became Democrats or not like left
right but capital D and it was always
because it worked and then the unwinding
of it that we don't ask if it unwinds
you know, our it will we will not be
protected
>> and it it's just the dialogue we have
currently is not acknowledging what's
going to happen politically, what is
happening politically. The the wealth
tax is a derivative of this because
everyone knows the wealth tax isn't
going to help the poor. It's just going
to [ __ ] the rich and that's enough to
get it done. M
>> and if if that's happening, just imagine
what's going to happen when it's like
there's going to be 50 unlikable people
with all the money.
[laughter]
>> Anybody here like that? And you guys are
doing well.
>> No. No. I I I want to get back to to
kind of the conversation about how um
how we ensure that the Department of War
continues to lead on AI because I think
this has been top of mind for everyone
in the room for the last 48 hours. um
our adversaries are looking at you know
contracting wars um that are playing out
in press releases you know what is your
view on how we can ensure that we win
this AI race against the PRC if you if
you're giving advice to all the founders
and CEOs of of you know the the the
>> first thing part of what I'm doing and
part of the reason I mean besides your
charm and importance part of the reason
I want to be here is uh I want
my reputation in the valley every you
always have reputations my reputation
which the rep I'm not even saying the
reputation is true. But in my case, like
I'm viewed as the batshit crazy guy who
is often telling you something you don't
want to hear and you may not like but is
probably right.
And
>> that's true.
>> So yeah, [laughter]
and that's why I want you to send this
first step. We have to they're not
understanding the stakes and what I
nothing's going to happen till people
understand the stakes. This will affect
you. Now then the question is like what
Hollywood did is Hollywood got together
the whole rating system was Hollywood
realized if we don't do rating ratings
Washington's going to and Washington is
going to butcher it
>> and let's even say Washington doesn't
want to butcher it but like it it
doesn't understand the metier
>> so the first step is everybody and I'm
already on the phone with people saying
okay great I understand your issue but
you realize
the wolves are at the gate and they
already have tasted blood.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh the second step is we have to find
ways where we get together and say okay
like if you just want to go through the
issues yes there are you know using
technologies in the context of
eviscerating
fourth amendment rights in America is a
is something left and right in this
country actually don't want. It's a
caricature to believe that either side
wants it. There are people on the
honestly I'm in private rooms. There are
people on the left who don't care about
these issues who pretend to do it in p
do in public but there are people and
there are people on the right who
pretend not to care who do care. Both
parties have significant coalitions and
the American people cares care and it's
in our constitution. But then you have
to get be very granular about what's
going to happen on the battlefield
because they're the the two issues
Americans care about are their
prosperity and their safety. So if the
if if the two things that Silicon Valley
has to figure out is is what are we
going to how are we going to ethically
talk about what's going to happen to our
economy in my view you have you could
create a lot of prosperity with trade
shaped people. Uh, okay. But what is
going to happen to the white collar
workers? And what are we going to do?
That that's one issue. And then we we're
not going to agree, but we have to have
something like a we're going to do these
initiatives just like Hollywood did. And
then you're going to have to have a
discussion on the battlefield where you
know the rebuttable presumption meaning
it doesn't happen is that the we are
going to do the maximal amount to make
sure our war fighters come home safely.
And if you are sitting in Silicon Valley
making an argument that somehow would
evviscerate that or conversely you're
not able to understand what Silicon
Valley is saying. Meaning there's going
to have to be a medium without going
into details on all these breakdowns cuz
I was in the middle of it and I want to
stay in the middle of it. There there
are substantive issues and there are
cultural issues.
>> If we could get rid of the cultural
misunderstanding, we could get pretty
close to agreements here. Yeah. But you
you're dealing with worlds that never
ever ever talk. Yes.
>> And don't have an ability to talk to
each other.
>> Yeah. Well, and you've been building a
bridge between these cultures for 20
years. I mean, that's what's so
interesting. I mean, that's in some ways
why we have this conference is to bring
together people who speak two different
languages, very different value sets,
and try to get them aligned. I I'd love
your advice for these founders who maybe
are new. You know, it's sort of like
that meme, the first time meme uh with
Cohen Brothers film, you know, where
it's like a lot of these people are
having their first conversations with
the Department of War or they don't or
they maybe they don't have any family in
the military, maybe they've met never
met a war fighter. What is your advice
to some of these CEOs who are maybe new
to these conversations that you've been
having for for 20 years now?
>> Well, the best thing you could do is go
to Iowa or go to a base and have a like
I don't think look put this way um maybe
the first time
It's probably not PG, but you know, I'm
happily not married, not divorced, so
don't follow how I live. But you don't
have to. Maybe if you're going to meet
somebody, you really want to oppress it.
Maybe not. Maybe you have an advantage
if it's your third girlfriend or
boyfriend, not your first. Like, go have
a conversation with somebody. Like if
you're going to meet a general or
somebody like that and you've never
talked to somebody who's actually done
something on the battlefield or someone
who has family who's done something on
the battlefield and you don't have any
and because of that you don't have an
ability to empathize with their
perspective
that's probably a huge mistake.
>> Yeah.
>> And I that's probably going to backfire.
Last secondly though you have to be
honest aware about where your aptitude
is. Mhm.
>> Like you know um Silicon Valley tech
builders broadly defined hardware,
software, AI. I would say we build in
the military context uh essentially uh
software scaffolding much more like in a
weird way more more like hardware
software but it's in software uh
managing LLMs. Um uh it it is the single
biggest mistake people make in this area
is because they're intelligent in one
area, they assume they're intelligent in
all areas. And a big failure mechanism
in the valley is every valley person is
forced to present as if they're the
smartest in all areas at all times.
>> And that's like if you don't know who
the mark is, you're the mark.
>> Yeah. Like if you think you're the
smartest. So I I'm dyslexic and I think
one of the reasons I've done so well is
I do think I'm one of the better people
at certain things. At least I believe it
and I know I'm not at everything. It's a
very small it's like but a failure mode
for the valley is I'm the smartest on
every issue. I for example I need to be
the person negotiating this contract.
Yeah.
>> What if you have no aptitude for that?
Mhm.
>> Just because you can do X does not mean
you've imputed high aptitude at Y. In
fact, it's very unlikely it's true.
>> Yeah.
>> It's it's almost certain that you're
just not smart enough to realize how bad
you are.
>> That's probably one of the most
important lessons for for company
builders in the room. I actually I I
want to um end the conversation on
Palunteer is the OG American Dynamism
company. Um I think a lot of our
founders in this room are indebted.
They've worked for you. They've um you
know built their playbooks inside of
Palunteer. They've built new companies
that, you know, are are epic in their
own right, but they started at Palanteer
in many cases. And so I want to dive
into you. You brought up the neurode
divergent fellowship. It's one of my
favorite things you've ever done. You've
done a lot of great things, but I think
it's it's one of the most extraordinary
um stands that you've taken in the
company, but you've always looked for
people who are different and somehow
cultivated them and brought together
people who are Democrats, Republicans,
on the right, on the left, people who
are of all walks of life. How do you
lead such a diverse group of people
especially at scale like at the scale
you are?
>> Well, I mean it's always hard to know
when you're re like I I I view myself as
an artist. So, you're really, it's like,
well, how do you create the art? And
it's funny because I I mean, I look, I I
like the freedom money gives me, and I I
certainly don't want to like do some
[ __ ] philanthropy to prove that I'm
good when because I did something bad
because I think what we do is very
important. Um, but it's like at the end
of the day, it's like an artistic thing.
But, you know, I had it's always
helpful. I had my parents are among the
most talented people I've ever met and I
feel they don't agree with me that you
know like they should have they could
like it's kind of weird I'm so famous
put it that way from and uh um I uh um
uh I I and I then there's the American
thing where we are I really believe in
the magical
liberating, inalienable right for all of
us to be individuals. And that's what I
see as particularly moral and special in
the world. I don't like these things
that like I I've been famously
anti-woke, but in the thing I find
offensive about it is actually that it's
people pretending to be different while
all being the same. And so I don't like
uh so I tend to gravitate towards people
who are unique and yeah, I don't really
care. their politics. I care about like
their ability to think and do. Um there
is an aptitude thing where can you
recognize somebody who is truly unique
in something you've not done yourself is
just something you're born with. Um I I
do think it's a form of neurode
divergence like outlier IQ is a the
certain way it's not that different than
being autistic. like you just can't
you're not going to you're not going to
decomp a problem the way somebody who is
all just normal smart will.
>> Um and I find that very very
charismatic. The trick to doing it is
you have to it's this very hard thing
where somebody who is the best I I
believe the palunteerians
while managed a palunteer and sometimes
in many and most cases presumably after
a palunteer I am helping them to express
something that only they can do at that
moment and if you look at our products
and what we've done it is actually true
even what we're doing in in like right
now all across the Middle East and
obviously ly in America, each single
product at each single part was built by
the one person in the world that could
have done it. But that and then I have
to somehow get them to do things that
they don't actually think are valuable
but on their terms. And that's basically
my job because at that level of
aptitude, you can't just say do this
idiot because they're like why would I
do that? You're the idiot. Uh and so um
and and then what I think is very
special about the Palunteerians,
ex-punteerians and current Palunteerians
is when you're at Palunteer, you're not
learning to to actually follow my
playbook.
>> You're learning to follow your playbook
where I'm inserting some things that may
not have occurred to you. Maybe you
don't know I'm doing that to make sure
that your playbook gets rid of your
dyslexia. Basically, I'm
anti-dislexifying
your playbook.
>> It but around you. And if you take like
the I don't know, there's so many really
important expentiterians. What you'll
see is they're a kind of classic people
and they're not going to build the same
company Palanteer was. They're also not
going to build the same company of the
next person as Palanteer. And that's why
they play such a disproportional role.
And at the end of the day, that's why
Poundier is like playing such a big role
because like Foundry, PG, Apollo,
Ontology, uh the management of Ontology,
Maven, which is like you know, we've
just like been able to target in a way
no other country can. It's like the
other countries are like what the
happened here like we were thinking
Afghanistan like what is this? meaning
our retreat like meaning and like like
America has reestablished a terrence.
>> That actually just happened. It's
happened in the last year.
>> Like that right, left, center, I don't
care what party you're in in private.
Obviously, you can't say this in public.
In private, that is a phenomenal asset
that America now has that it did not
have. And there are lots of reasons for
it, but a one maybe not the most
important is a concatenation of the most
unusual in some cases otherwise maybe
not fully functional talent built around
building something that was a absolutely
scandalous unpopular dream rejected by
many people called Maven.
And that's how this country and by the
way if we are going to outperform the
rest of the world uh our single
advantage is to augment neurodeivergent
highly individual people to be their
absolutely unique best and protect their
first second fourth and fifth amendment
rights so that they don't get screwed.
>> Absolutely. Well, again, the OG American
Dynamism founder, thank you so much for
all you've done for the country.
>> Thank you.
[music]